<?xml version="1.0"?>
<page title="About">
  <section title="What is Pingus?">
    <p>
      Pingus is 
      free <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lemmings">Lemmings<sup>tm</sup></a>-
      puzzle game covered 
      the <a href="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/gpl.html">
        GPL</a>. It features currently 77 playable levels and runs 
      a wide variety of operating systems (Linux, Windows, MacOSX, etc.)
    </p>
  </section>

  <section title="The Game">
    <p>
      Pingus has started at the end of 1998 with the simple goal 
      create a Free (as in freedom, not as in free beer)
      Lemmings<sup>tm</sup> clone. The <em>Free</em> means you get 
      sources and are allowed and encouraged to change and 
      them. You basically get everything that I used to create 
      game. In the years it has grown than quite a bit over 
      original goal and become something more than just a clone, 
      have original artwork, a built-in level editor, new actions,
      multiplayer and a few other features.
    </p>

    <p>
      If you don't know Lemmings<sup>tm</sup>, here comes a 
      introduction. It is a puzzle game developed in 
      by <a href="http://www.mobygames.com/company/sheet/companyId,146/">
        Design</a>. The player takes command in the game of a bunch 
      small animals and has to guide them through levels. Since 
      animals walk on their own, the player can only influence them 
      giving them commands, like <em>build a bridge</em>,
      <em>dig a hole</em> or <em>redirect all animals in the 
	direction</em>. The goal of each level is to reach the exit,
      for this multiple combination of commands are necessary.  
      game is presented in a 2D site view. For more information 
      might want to visit one of the 
      visit <a href="http://web.archive.org/web/20110718120402/http://www.deveria.com/alexis/lemmings/fanlinks.html">Lemmings<sup>tm</sup>
	fanpages</a> on the net.
    </p>

    <p>
      While Pingus is based on the idea of Lemmings<sup>tm</sup>, 
      however doesn't try to be an exact clone, it has included a 
      ideas of its own, like the worldmap or secret levels, 
      might be familiar from games the Super Mario World and 
      Nintendo games. It has also a few new actions, like the 
      which weren't presented in the original game. To get 
      impression of the look of the Pingus game you might want to 
      a look at some <a href="screenshots.html">screenshots</a>.
    </p>

  </section>
</page>
